A Guide to the Record Group Vertical Files, 1960s-present
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
- Record Group 14 - College of Architecture and Urban Studies (CAUS)
  - RG 14/12 - School of Public and International Affairs (SPIA)
    See also RG 37.
  - RG 14/13 - Myers-Lawson School of Construction
    The Myers-Lawson School of Construction was formed in 2006. However, courses in Building Construction [RG 14/3/3] were first offered in 1947 in the Architecture Department.
    May include Intelligent Infrastructure and Construction Complex; Department of Building Construction
    See also RG 14/3/3.
  - RG 14/14 - Washington-Alexandria Architecture Center
- Record Group 15 - College of Arts and Sciences [obsolete, July 2003]
  In 1961, the School of Science and General Studies formed out of several departments that were part of the School of Applied Sciences and Business [RG 12], which dissolved that year. However, some of the departments trace their roots back to the founding of the university in 1872.
  In 1963, the school became the School of Arts and Sciences and the next year became the College of Arts and Sciences, which dissolved in July 2003. Most of the liberal arts departments joined the newly-formed College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences [RG 48], while most of the science departments formed the College of Science [RG 47].
  Although the College of Arts and Sciences was discontinued in 2003, some files may include items through 2015 or later. May include Diplomat-in-Residence (Dr. Maurice Taylor); High School Science Teachers Summer Institute
  See also RG 47; RG 48.
  - RG 15 - College of Arts and Sciences (Information)
  - RG 15 - College of Arts and Sciences (Publications) [items also in Oversize Box 2]
  - RG 15a - Chalk Talks (Publications)
  - RG 15c - Degree Programs (Publications)
  - RG 15/1 - Office of the Dean
  - RG 15/2 - Individual Faculty
  - RG 15/3 - Department of Art [obsolete; see RG 14/10] [items also in Oversize Folder 1]
    Various drawing courses have been offered at Virginia Tech since 1872. In 1967, a curriculum in Art was developed and administered jointly by the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15] and the College of Architecture [RG 14]. The Art Department was established in the College of Arts and Sciences in 1976 and then became the Department of Art and Art History in 1983. The department joined the Division of Performing Arts to form the School of the Arts in the College of Arts and Sciences.
    In July 2003, the College of Arts and Sciences dissolved, and the School of the Arts became cross-collegial when the Department of Art and Art History moved to the College of Architecture and Urban Studies (CAUS), while the other departments joined the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences (CLAHS) [RG 48]. In 2008, the Department of Art and Art History separated from the other departments to become the School of Visual Arts [RG 14/10] in CAUS.
    May include The Armory Art Gallery [obsolete; see RG 14/10]; University Art Gallery; Owens Art Gallery
  - RG 15/4 - Department of Biochemistry [obsolete; see RG 13/7]
  - RG 15/5 - Department of Biology [obsolete; see RG 47/8]
    Biology courses have been offered at Virginia Tech since its beginning in 1872. In 1891, the Biology Department was formed. The department was divided into the departments of Botany and Plant Pathology and of Zoology and Animal Pathology in 1926. In 1935, the department was united again as the Biology Department. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences to the College of Science as the Department of Biological Sciences [RG 47/8] in 2003.
    May include Antarctic Expedition; Aquatic Ecology Group
  - RG 15/6 - Department of Chemistry [obsolete; see RG 47/6]
    Chemistry courses have been offered since 1872. However, the department has gone through several name and organizational changes: General and Analytical Chemistry, 1873-1883; Chemistry and Metallurgy, 1883-1887; Chemistry, Geology, and Mineralogy, 1887-1891; General Chemistry, Mineralogy, and Geology, 1891-1901; General and Industrial Chemistry, 1901-1902; Geology, Mineralogy, and Organic Chemistry, 1902-1903; General Chemistry, 1903-1904; Chemistry, 1904-1929; Chemistry and Chemical Engineering, 1929-1935; and Chemistry, 1935-present. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences to the College of Science [RG 47/6] in 2003.
    May include Howe Award; Glassblowing
  - RG 15/7 - Department of Computer Science [obsolete; see RG 18/21]
    Courses have been offered in Computer Science since 1968. It became a department in 1970. It was initially housed in the College of Arts and Sciences and later moved to the College of Engineering [RG 18/21].
  - RG 15/8 - Department of Economics [obsolete, 2003; see RG 16/5 and RG 47/11]
    Courses in economics have been offered under a variety of different names since at least 1904: English and Economics, 1904-1905; History and Economics, 1905-1916; Economics and Political Science, 1916-1917; Economics and History, 1924-1957; and a curriculum in Business Administration Department, 1957-1961. The Department of Economics was one of the founding departments [RG 16/5] within the College of Business [RG 16] when it formed in 1961. In 1989, the department moved to the College of Arts and Sciences. When the college dissolved in 2003, the Department of Economics became one of the founding departments [RG 47/11] within the College of Science [RG 47].
  - RG 15/9 - Department of Physics [obsolete; see RG 47/4]
    Physics courses have been offered in some form since 1872. The Department of Physics and Mechanics was formed in 1883, followed by Physics and Electrical Engineering in 1891, Mathematics and Physics in 1898, and Physics in 1904. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences to the College of Science [RG 47/4] in 2003.
    May include Nuclear reactor [see also RG 18/9; RG 6/3/2b, Robeson Hall]
  - RG 15/10 - Department of English [obsolete; see RG 48/4] [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    Courses in English have been offered since 1872 under different course and department names and organizations: English Language and Literature, 1872-1883; English Language, Literature, and Criticism, 1883-1887; English and Latin, 1887-1891; English, History, and Political Economy, 1891-1898; English, History, and Political Economy, 1891-1898; English, History, and Spanish, 1898-1902; English and Spanish, 1902-1903; English and Political Economy, 1903-1904; English and Economics, 1904-1905; English, 1905-1958; English and Foreign Languages, 1958-1965; and English, 1965-present. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences to the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences [RG 48/4] in 2003.
    May include Highlands Conference on Literacy (1978); Writing Center
  - RG 15/11 - Department of Foreign Languages and Literature [obsolete; see RG 48/13]
    Foreign language courses have been offered since 1872 under different names and organizations: Latin, 1873-1887; English and Latin, 1887-1891; English, History, and Spanish, 1898-1902; English and Spanish, 1902-1903; Modern Languages and Latin, 1915-1920; Foreign Languages, 1920-1958; English and Foreign Languages, 1958-1965; and Foreign Languages, beginning 1965.
    The Department was later renamed Foreign Languages and Literature until Fall 2017, when it became the Department of Modern and Classical Languages and Literatures. The department moved from College of Arts and Sciences to the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences [RG 48/13] in 2003.
    May include Language Lab
  - RG 15/12 - Department of Geosciences [obsolete; see RG 47/3]
    The first degree in Geology was given in 1910. Courses in the geological sciences have been offered under the following departments: Chemistry, Geology, and Mineralogy, 1887-1991; General Chemistry, Mineralogy, and Geology, 1891-1901; Mineralogy, 1901-1902; Geology, Mineralogy, and Organic Chemistry, 1902-1903; Geology and Mineralogy, 1903-1907; Applied Geology, 1907-1920; Geology, 1920-1955; and Geological Sciences, beginning 1955. The department was later renamed the Department of Geosciences. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences to the College of Science [RG 47/3] in 2003.
    May include Archaeology; Paleontology; Bailey-Law Collection, Natural Sciences Collection; Earthquakes; Seismological Station
    - RG 15/12a - Seminars, 1981-1985
    - RG 15/12b - Seminars, 1986-1991
    - RG 15/12c - Seminars, 1992-1995
    - RG 15/12d - Seminars, undated
  - RG 15/13 - Department of History [obsolete; see RG 48/5]
    History courses have been offered since 1872 under various names and organizations: English, History, and Political Economy, 1891-1898; English, History, and Spanish, 1898-1902; History, 1902-1906; History and Economics, 1906-1916; Economics and History, 1924-1957; courses offered through Business Administration Department, 1957-1961; History and Political Science, 1961-1965; and History, 1961-present. The Department of History moved from the College of Arts and Sciences to the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences [RG 48/5] in 2003.
  - RG 15/14 - Department of Mathematics [obsolete; see RG 47/13]
    Mathematics courses have been offered since 1872 under different names and organizations of the department: Mathematics, 1872-1891; Mathematics and Civil Engineering, 1891-1894; Mathematics, 1894-1897; Mathematics and Physics, 1897-1904; and Mathematics, 1904-present. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15/14] to the College of Science [RG 47/13] in 2003.
    - RG 15/14/1 - Math Emporium
    - RG 15/14/2 - Interdisciplinary Center for Applied Mathematics (ICAM)
  - RG 15/15 - Department of Performing Arts and Communications (PAC) [obsolete; see RG 48/3 and RG 48/7]
    Music courses were first offered in 1965 and theatre arts courses in 1967. In 1970, the Department of Performing Arts and Communications (PAC) formed in the College of Arts and Sciences (CAS) with courses in theatre arts, music, and communications. PAC split into three departments: Music [RG 15/15/2], Theatre Arts [RG 15/15/3], and Communication [RG 15/15/1]. In 1983, the departments of music and of theatre arts combined into the Division of Performing Arts [RG 15/15/3c]. The Division joined with the Department of Art and Art History [RG 15/3] to form the School of the Arts in CAS.
    In July 2003, CAS dissolved, and the School of the Arts became cross-collegial when the Department of Art and Art History moved to the College of Architecture and Urban Studies (CAUS) [RG 14], while the other departments joined the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences (CLAHS) [RG 48].
    The Cinema program developed in the Department of Communication [RG 48/3], which also moved to CLAHS in 2003. In 2008, the Department of Art and Art History separated to become the School of Visual Arts [RG 14/10] in CAUS. Cinema separated from the Department of Communication and formed the School of Performing Arts and Cinema with the departments of Music and of Theatre Arts. The School was renamed the School of Performing Arts [RG 48/7] in 2013.
    - RG 15/15 - Department of Performing Arts and Communications (Information)
    - RG 15/15 - Department of Performing Arts and Communications (Publications)
    - RG 15/15b - Calendars of Events
    - RG 15/15c - Summer Arts Festival (Publications) [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    - RG 15/15/1 - Communications Department [obsolete; see RG 48/3]
      In 1970, the Department of Performing Arts and Communications (PAC) [RG 15/15] formed in the College of Arts and Sciences (CAS) with courses in theatre arts, music, and communications. PAC split into three departments: Music [RG 15/15/2], Theatre Arts [RG 15/15/3], and Communication. In July 2003, CAS dissolved, and the Department of Communication [RG 48/3] moved to the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences (CLAHS). The Cinema program developed in the department but later separated and joined the departments of Music and of Theatre Arts as the School of Performing Arts and Cinema. This was renamed the School of Performing Arts [RG 48/7] in 2013.
      May include former Debate Club [see also RG 31/14; RG 9/3, 1/24/1975]; Speech Arts Society; Journalism
      - RG 15/15/1a - Communications Department Newsletter [obsolete; see RG 48/3]
    - RG 15/15/2 - Music Department [obsolete; see RG 48/7] [items also in Oversize Box 2]
      Music courses were first offered in 1965. In 1970, the Department of Performing Arts and Communications (PAC) formed with courses in theatre arts, music, and communications. PAC split into three departments: Music [RG 15/15/2], Theatre Arts [RG 15/15/3], and Communication [RG 15/15/1]. In 1983, the departments of music and of theatre arts combined into the Division of Performing Arts [RG 15/15/3c]. The Division joined with the Department of Art and Art History [RG 15/3] to form the School of the Arts in the College of Arts and Sciences (CAS).
      In 2008, the Department of Art and Art History separated from the other departments to become the School of Visual Arts [RG 14/10] in CAUS. The Cinema program developed in the Department of Communication [RG 48/3] but later separated from Communication and joined the departments of Music and of Theatre Arts as the School of Performing Arts and Cinema. This was renamed the School of Performing Arts [RG 48/7] in 2013.
      May include Audubon Quarter [see also RG 31/8/14]; Campus Orchestra Development Association (CODA); Virginia Tech Showmen [formerly Varsity Glee Club]
      See also RG 15/15/3c; RG 31/8; RG 48/7.
      - RG 15/15/2 - Music (Information)
      - RG 15/15/2 - Music (Publications)
      - RG 15/15/2a - Salon Series (Publications) [items also in Oversize Box 2]
        May include New Virginians
      - RG 15/15/2b - Recitals (Publications)
        May include Band
      - RG 15/15/2c - Bach's Lunch (Publications) [items also in Oversize Box 2]
        May include Songs of VPI incl. Moonlight & VPI, Tech Triumph, Ut Prosim [see also RG 40/8]
    - RG 15/15/3 - Theatre Arts Department [obsolete; see RG 48/7] [items also in Oversize Box 2]
      Theatre arts courses were first offered in 1967. In 1970, the Department of Performing Arts and Communications (PAC) formed in the College of Arts and Sciences (CAS) with courses in theatre arts, music, and communications. PAC split into three departments: Music [RG 15/15/2], Theatre Arts [RG 15/15/3], and Communication [RG 15/15/1]. In 1983, the departments of music and of theatre arts combined into the Division of Performing Arts [RG 15/15/3c]. The Division joined with the Department of Art and Art History [RG 15/3] to form the School of the Arts in CAS.
      In 2008, the Department of Art and Art History separated to become the School of Visual Arts [RG 14/10] in CAUS. The Cinema program developed in the Department of Communication [RG 48/3] but later separated and joined the departments of Music and of Theatre Arts as the School of Performing Arts and Cinema. This was renamed the School of Performing Arts [RG 48/7] in 2013.
      May include Dramatic groups [see also RG 31/4]; Dramatic productions
      See also RG 15/15/3c; RG 31/4; RG 48/7.
      - RG 15/15/3 - Theatre Arts (Information)
      - RG 15/15/3 - Theatre Arts (Publications)
      - RG 15/15/3a - Plays (Publications) [items also in Oversize Box 2]
        May include University Players; Tech Players [see also RG 31/4/2]
      - RG 15/15/3b - Calendars of Events (Publications)
      - RG 15/15/3c - Division of Performing Arts [obsolete; see RG 48/7] [items in Oversize Box 2]
        In 2008, the Department of Art and Art History separated to become the School of Visual Arts [RG 14/10] in CAUS. The Cinema program developed in the Department of Communication [RG 48/3] but later Cinema separated from Communication and joined the departments of Music and of Theatre Arts as the School of Performing Arts and Cinema. This was renamed the School of Performing Arts [RG 48/7] in 2013.
  - RG 15/16 - Department of Political Science [obsolete; see RG 48/15]
    Courses in political economy were first offered in 1875. The different names and organizational structures that political science courses have been offered under include English, History, and Political Economy, 1891-1898; English, History, and Spanish, 1898-1902; History, 1902-1906; History and Economics, 1906-1916; Economics and History, 1924-1957; Business Administration, 1957-1961; History and Political Science, 1961-1965; and Political Science, 1965-present. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences to the College of Liberarl Arts and Human Sciences [RG 48/15] in 2003.
    May include Pre-Law program
  - RG 15/17 - Department of Psychology [obsolete; see RG 47/7]
    Prior to 1965, psychology courses were offered in the Vocational Education Department [RG 17/6]. The Department of Psychology and Sociology was formed in 1965, but the departments separated into the Department of Psychology and Department of Sociology [RG 15/19] in 1968. The department moved from College of Arts and Sciences to College of Science [RG 47/7] in 2003.
    May include Psychological Service Center
  - RG 15/18 - Department of Statistics [obsolete; see RG 47/9]
    From 1946 to 1949, courses in statistics were taught as part of the Department of Agriculture Economics, Rural Sociology, and Statistics, which later became the Department of Agricultural and Applied Economics [RG 13/3]. In 1949, the Department of Statistics was formed. The first bachelors degree in statistics was awarded in 1948. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15/18] to the College of Science [RG 47/9] in 2003.
    - RG 15/18/1 - Statistical Consulting Center
  - RG 15/19 - Department of Sociology [obsolete; see RG 48/11]
    Rural sociology courses were offered as early as 1872. Since that time, sociology courses have been offered under the following departments: Agricultural Economics and Rural Sociology, 1929-1933; Agricultural Economics, 1933-1940; Agricultural Economics, Rural Sociology, and Statistics, 1946-1948; Agricultural Economics and Rural Sociology, 1948-1965; Psychology and Sociology (1965-68); and Sociology, 1965-1968; and Sociology, 1968-present. The department moved from the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15/19] to the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences [RG 48/11] in 2003.
  - RG 15/20 - Department of Geography [obsolete, 2003; see RG 45/10]
    Courses in geography were offered as early as 1872. Prior to 1973, geography classes were offered through Courses in General Arts and Sciences. In 1973, a Program in Geography was offered through the College of Arts and Sciences (CAS). The Geography Department was established in 1978. The department moved from CAS [RG 15/20] to the College of Natural Resources and Environment (CNRE) [RG 45/10] in 2003.
  - RG 15/21 - Department of Philosophy and Religion [obsolete; see RG 48/6 and RG 48/14]
    Moral philosophy courses had been offered as early as 1872 and religion courses since 1954. The Department of Philosophy and Religion [RG 15/21] was formed in 1955. The department split in July 1983 into the departments of Philosophy and of Religion. In 1994, the Department of Religion became the Religious Studies Program in the Center for Interdisciplinary Studies [RG 15/27; RG 38]. At some point, Religious Studies merged with the Judaic Studies Program [RG 15/26] and Appalachian Studies [RG 42]]. In July 2003, the departments moved to the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences as the Department of Philosophy [RG 48/14] and the Department of Religion and Culture [RG 48/6].
    See also RG 15/26; RG 15/27; RG 38; RG 42; RG 48/6; RG 48/14.
  - RG 15/22 - Center for the Study of Science in Society [obsolete; see RG 48/12] [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    May include Science and Technology Studies (STS)
  - RG 15/23 - International Studies Program [obsolete; see RG 48/15]
  - RG 15/24 - Women's Studies [obsolete; see RG 15/19]
    Women's Studies merged into the Department of Sociology [RG 15/19].
    - RG 15/24/1 - Women's Week [obsolete; see RG 5/6/7] [items also in Oversize Box 2]
      The Women's Studies Program [RG 15/24] began Women's Week in 1982. In 1995, it was consolidated with Women's History Month [RG 15/24/2] into Women's Month, under the auspices of the Women's Center [RG 5/6/7].
      - RG 15/24/1 - Women's Week (Information) [obsolete; see RG 5/6/7]
      - RG 15/24/1 - Women's Week (Publications) [obsolete; see RG 5/6/7]
    - RG 15/24/2 - Women's History Month [obsolete; see RG 5/6/7]
      The Women's Studies Program [RG 15/24] began Women's History Month in 1993. In 1995, it was consolidated with Women's Week [RG 15/24/1] into Women's Month, under the auspices of the Women's Center [RG 5/6/7].
  - RG 15/25 - Black Studies Program [obsolete; see RG 15/19] [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    The Black Studies Program merged into the Department of Sociology [RG 15/19].
  - RG 15/26 - Judaic Studies Program [obsolete; see RG 48/6]
  - RG 15/27 - Center for Interdisciplinary Studies [obsolete; see RG 38] [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    May include Choices and Challenges forum [see also RG 15/27/1; RG 39/1]
  - RG 15/28 - Service Learning Center
  - RG 15/29 - School of Education [obsolete; see RG 48/9]
    Courses in education have been offered in specific programs throughout the history of the university, including Agricultural Education (1918); Physical Education, Home Economics Education, and Vocational Industrial Education (1921); Industrial Arts Education (1946); Business Education (1950); and Distributive Education (1954). In 1951, the Board of Visitors approved a Master of Education degree, which was available in vocational academic areas on the Blacksburg campus and other areas on the Women's Division at Radford.
    A Department of Education was founded in the College of Arts and Sciences starting 1965, and the College of Education [RG 17] was established on July 1, 1971. In 1996, the College of Education merged with the College of Human Resources to form the College of Human Resources and Education [RG 19].
    See also RG 17; RG 19; RG 48/9.
  - RG 15/30 - Departments of Apparel, Housing, and Resource Management; Human Development; and Teaching and Learning [obsolete]
    The Department of Human Development [RG 48/8] and the Department of Apparel, Housing, and Resource Management [RG 48/10] moved to the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences [RG 48] in 2003.
    See also RG 48/8; RG 48/10.
- Record Group 16 - Pamplin College of Business
  Courses in business have been offered since 1881, and the Department of Business Administration was established in 1924. The School of Applied Science and Business Administration formed in 1950 out of the Department. In 1960, the School dissolved, and several departments moved to the School of Business, established the same year and renamed the College of Business in 1964. The college was renamed Pamplin College of Business for two alumni, Robert B. Pamplin and his son, Robert B. Pamplin Jr., in 1986.
  May include Center for Economic Research [obsolete]; Center for Business Intelligence and Analytics; Bond And Securities Investing by Students (BASIS); KPMG Master of Accounting with Data and Analytics Program; MBA programs; Pamplin Hackathon; Ethics Week; Business Horizons career fair
  - RG 16 - College of Business (Information)
  - RG 16 - College of Business (Publications)
  - RG 16/1 - Office of the Dean
  - RG 16/2 - Individual Faculty
  - RG 16/3 - Department of Accounting and Information Systems
    The Department of Accounting and Information Systems was formerly Department of Accounting.
    May include the Beta Alpha Psi, Gamma Lambda Chapter
  - RG 16/4 - Department of Business Administration [obsolete]